Finding Aid for Lucia Isabelle Voorhees Grimes Papers 1900-1977
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Lucia Isabelle Voorhees Grimes Papers
1900-1977
Grimes, Lucia Isabelle Voorhees, 1877-1978.
Suffragist, leader of the Michigan Branch of the National Woman's Party, and candidate for the Michigan legislature in 1924. Correspondence, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, periodicals and other materials concerning her activities in the Michigan Equal Suffrage Association, the Legislative Council of Michigan Women, the National Woman's Party, and the Republican Party; and photographs.
851380; Aa/2
4 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Lucia Grimes (donor no. 2494 ) began donating materials to the library in 1948. Additional papers were received n 1971 and 1978.
The collection is open for research.
Lucia Isabelle Voorhees Grimes was born on August 28, 1877 in Princeville, Illinois. She graduated from high school in 1895 and, after teaching for one year in a one-room country school, she enrolled in 1896 at Illinois State Normal School in Normal, Illinois. After a year's teaching in the Pekin, Illinois, high school (1898-1899), she enrolled at the University of Michigan, and graduated in 1902, with a BA, receiving at the same time a teacher's certificate in history and English. She taught for two years at the Escanaba, Michigan high school, and returned to the University of Michigan in 1904, enrolling in the graduate school. In 1905, she received her Master's degree in history. After two more years of teaching in Coldwater, Michigan and Oklahoma City, she married George Lyman Grimes on April 29, 1907.
During World War I and for nearly ten years afterward, Lucia Grimes worked with her husband as purchasing agent for the family firm of Grimes Molding Machine Company in Detroit. In 1928 she joined the faculty of Cass Technical High School in Detroit, where she taught history and English until her retirement in 1948.
Soon after her move to Detroit in 1907, Lucia Grimes became an active participant in the women's suffrage movement. Her first association was with the College Suffrage League; later she was one of the organizers of the Equal Suffrage League of Wayne County and chairman of its Political Department in which position she prepared a card file about each member of the Michigan legislature. She later prepared a similar file on all members of Congress for the National Women's Suffrage Association.
Lucia Grimes played a leading role in the National Woman's Party as one of the organizers of its Michigan branch. She worked as a challenger in the 1913 and 1917 elections when a women's suffrage amendment was put before Michigan voters, and took part in the preparations that led to the passage of the bill to give Michigan women presidential suffrage. By 1918, as legislative chair of the Michigan Federation of Women's Clubs, she was one of the leaders of the effort to have the state ratify the 19th amendment. In 1920, Michigan became the second state to ratify the 19th amendment.
After passage, Lucia Grimes continued her efforts to bring women in to the political arena. She was recording secretary of the Campaign League of Detroit, and president of the Wayne County Republican Club. In 1920, she was elected chair of the Legislative Council of Michigan Women.
The Grimes papers have been arranged into the following series: Correspondence; Other Papers (non-correspondence); Subject files; Bills introduced in the Michigan legislature; Newspaper clippings; Printed material; Scrapbooks; and Miscellaneous.
Subjects:
Congressional Union for Woman Suffrage (U.S.); Detroit (Mich.); Detroit Equal Suffrage Club.; Elections--Michigan--1912.; Elections--Michigan--1914.; Elections--Michigan--1916.; Elections--Michigan--1924.; Grimes, Lucia Isabelle Voorhees, 1877-1978.; Legislative Council of Michigan Women.; Presidents--United States--Election--1916.; Republican Party (Mich.); Women--Michigan--Societies and clubs.; Women--Suffrage--Michigan.; Women's rights--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Aged persons.; Celebrations.; Classrooms--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Grimes, George Lyman.; Grimes, Lucia Isabelle Voorhees, 1877-1978.; Suffragettes.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; Women.
Contributors:
League of Women Voters (U.S.); Michigan Equal Suffrage Association.; Michigan State Federation of Women's Clubs.; National Civil Service League.; National Woman's Party.; Paul, Alice, 1885-1977.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Correspondence
  - Undated, 1913-1977; 22 folders (Box 1)
- Other Papers
  - Undated, 1902-1921; 11 folders (Box 1)
  - 1922-1977, 24 folders (Box 2)
- Subject files
  - Questionnaire concerning equal rights for women, 1932; 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Wayne County Woman's Republican Club, 1920-1960; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - League of Equal Suffrage Societies of Detroit minutes, 1911-1912 (Box 3)
  - "A History of the Suffrage Movement as Related to Michigan and Detroit" by Lucia Grimes, 1952 (Box 3)
  - Notes concerning the history of the suffrage movement in Michigan, 1952; 2 folders (Box 3)
- Bills introduced in the Michigan legislature
  - 1917, 1919-1939; 3 folders (Box 3)
- Newspaper clippings
  - 1912-1938, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 1945-1977 (Box 3)
- Printed material
  - Undated, 1912-1945; 15 folders (Box 3)
- Scrapbooks
  - Scrapbook concerning the suffrage movement, 1915 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook concerning women's rights, 1924-1925 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1912-1943; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook containing tributes from Republicans to LVG, 1968 (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous
  - Papers concerning suffrage pageant, 1925 (Box 4)
  - Papers of Marian H. McClench, 1922-1924 (Box 4)
    (McClench was secretary of the Legislative Council of Michigan Women)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Transcript of oral interview conducted by Pat Pilling, 1974 (Box 4)
    The file also includes 2 audio cassettes of the interview
  - Outstanding Achievement Award-University of Michigan (Box 4)
  - Photographs, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Student notebooks and papers mainly from extension classes, circa 1937; 2 volumes; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Outline of Work-Wayne County Equal Suffrage Organization, circa 1912 (Folder 1)
Selective Index to Correspondence
Congressional Union for Woman Suffrage (U.S.)
1916-1918
League of Women Voters (U.S.)
1921-1922 and 1924
Legislative Council of Michigan Women.
1922-1939
Michigan Equal Suffrage Association.
1913-1916
Michigan State Federation of Women's Clubs.
1919, 1921, 1923-1924, 1929, 1931, 1933
National Civil Service League.
1922-1924, 1935
National Woman's Party.
1916-1920, 1922-1923, 1927-1941, 1945
Paul, Alice, 1885-1977.
1916-1920, 1930, 1933-1934, 1938
Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.
May 1932, May 1933, Feb. 1934, March 1934, August 1935, March 1939